[Music]
in a leafy suburb of Toronto lives one
of the world's most controversial
thinkers Thank You Jordan
okay psychology professor Jordan
Peterson caused a storm in late 2016
with a couple of YouTube videos about
changes to the law in Canada around
gender pronouns you came in from where I
came in from London last night this
University campus became a battleground
like if I asked you would you please
news daytime runners for me what what it
would depend on what hoops do you want
us to jump for those are my pronouns
those there's no motivation no I know no
one ever has his opponents accused him
of being transphobic many others rallied
to support him his job was threatened he
refused to back down he claimed a new
law pushed forward an authoritarian
political agenda I was being asked as
everyone is to use a certain set of
words that I think are the constructions
of people who have a political ideology
that I don't believe in and that I also
regard is as dangerous to me they're
there they're there an attempt to
control language and in a direction that
isn't happening organically it's not
happening naturally but by force and by
Fiat and I would say by force because
there's legislative power behind them so
like these made-up words Z and xur and
that sort of thing what about the
Petersons this wasn't really about
pronouns
this was a surface reflection of a much
deeper crisis the legislation itself and
the policies were signifying a crisis a
disjunction in Western society that was
was far of which the gender pronoun
argument was only a tiny tendril I put
my finger on a nerve
as time passed many of those who flocked
to his videos for an attack on political
correctness became hooked by his message
of transformation and transcendence and
began calling him one of the most
profound thinkers of the time as a
journalist and filmmaker of a TV
networks like channel 4 in the BBC I'm
trained to be skeptical of these kind of
grand claims but over the last few
months of listening to his lectures I
become convinced that what he is saying
is that significant which is why I've
come all the way to Toronto to interview
him Peterson has been studying belief
systems his whole life and how the most
utopian ideas can create the worst
outcomes and he's concluded that only
appreciation and integration of the
great ideas of the past would protect us
from the same things happening again
I've always been surprised that I've
been able to teach what I've been
teaching in the universities because
I've always regarded it as crazily
radical in a sense you know it's crazily
radical in a conservative way well I
don't know what to make of that your
teaching is crazy radical in a
conservative way yeah I mean it's in a
conservative way because I think that
the past is not only has value its we
cannot live without the integration of
the past no more than you can live as an
individual without integrating your past
I mean we're historical creatures right
and and we without if we're not united
can't consciously with the past then
were divided internally and socially and
that has consequences so some of them
are playing it themselves
so in the political divisions in the
current world but the consequences can
be fatal his fascination with the nature
of belief system started when he was a
young man haunted by the threat of
nuclear annihilation during the Cold War
I was trying to solve this terrible
puzzle that confronted me for and many
other people about how it was that human
beings got themselves in such a tangle
about what they believed such a tangle
that we were pointing the ultimate
weapons of destruction at one another
which by the way we are still doing and
I thought okay well I understand that we
need their belief systems they orient us
and that means there will be conflict
between belief systems and that can be a
catastrophe and that's being played out
everywhere again in very many ways
what's the solution to that well one
possibility is there's no solution it's
just mayhem all the way around could be
the case but it seemed to me as I delved
into it that the proper solution to that
was to live properly
he believes the answers for how to live
properly are all around us if we look
carefully the artists get there before
the philosophers long before the
philosophers the dramatists get there
way before the artists even and so we've
figured it out we represented it in art
and literature and music and drama and
then we're on the cusp so to speak of
understanding it in a fully articulated
manner and not a moment too soon so what
is that idea basically that there's a
hidden story of transformation and
transcendence and it's encoded in a
mythology in our religion in our biology
and in our actions Petersen is reviving
the thought of Carl Jung the renegade
psychologist who delve deeply into the
human subconscious to develop the theory
of archetypes Universal patterns of
being such as the Divine Mother
shared by all in the collective
unconscious the way it looks to me is
that we embody a lot of information in
our action and our action has developed
as a consequence of imitating other
people and not only the people the
people around us but of course the
people around us imitated the people who
came before them and those people in
metate the people who came before them
and so on so far back that it's as far
back as you can go and so you embody
these patterns of behavior that are
extremely informative that you don't
understand that are a consequence of
collective imitation across the
centuries and then those patterns can
become manifest as figures of the
imagination and those figures of
imagination are the distillation zuv
patterns of behavior and so as the
distillation zuv patterns of behavior
they have content and it's not you that
content it's you could even think about
it as content that's evolved although
it's culturally transmitted it's content
that's evolved and so these figures of
the imagination can reveal the structure
of reality to you and that's what
happened with Jung and that's what he
described in the red book and that was
what permeated his psychology a
psychology that was based on the
presupposition that the fundamental
archetypal structures of religious
belief were not pathological not
deceitful not protective in some
delusional sense against the fear of
death but quite the contrary the very
stories that enabled us to move forward
as confident human beings in the face of
chaos itself and it's conceivable
I think perhaps probable that nothing
more important conceptually happened in
the 20th century than that because it
was the first time post enlightenment
that a rapprochement between the
intellect and the underlying religious
archetypal sub structure occurred you
have in the capacious intellect of Jung
and the same thing happened to some
degree with Piaget
the religious domain and the factual
domain were brought back together and
the fact of Jung's enduring and
increasing popularity and influence I
would say is a direct consequence of
that Peterson is reviving young and
grounding his discoveries in the latest
neuroscience explaining how these
mythological archetypes are encoded in
our brains and bodies tying together
mythology psychology morality and
religion with science you're adrift
without it you have to you have to have
a conscious relationship with the
archetypes there's no way if you don't
then you're susceptible to possession
that's basically or to or to despair so
and no wonder well you've got to have
axioms so the run yeah seems are the
archetypes yes that's where they exist
you see a certain axis biological
structures there at least that yeah
they're preexisting they're pre-existing
categories of perception in the Kantian
sense that's a good way of thinking
about it is that you know that the peer
empiricist thinks that you get all your
information from the outside world right
but that's not true because you bring on
a priori interpretive framework to the
world and that's instantiated
biologically but then it's also
enculturated so separating the archetype
from the underlying biological reality
isn't easy so you have the snake you
have the propensity to to perceive
reptilian predators the manner in which
those things are represented in the
culture fill those holes essentially and
so that can summarize the language
instinct so yeah that's right exactly
it's the same thing it's the same thing
like the archetypes are manifestations
of the universal grammar grammar of
emotion and motivation that's a good way
of thinking about it now they may be
more than that
these are some things we have to recover
these timeless truths but most of all
the idea of transcendental truth itself
the logos it's the idea of the logos
most means something like coherent
interpersonal communication of the truth
it's the action of the logos that
extracts order from chaos will not
survive without it the West will die
without the rebirth of the logos because
the West is that so without gone it's
gone and we've seen what's arisen to
replace it while there's fascism
there's communism and then there's the
New Age mess because it's a mess and
most of its wish fulfillment and fantasy
and inability to there's creativity in
it but there's no capacity to edit
whatsoever
there's no coherence and so that's stuff
so weak that anyone with any commitment
can just push it aside and there's no
justification for the for the Marxism
and or for the fascism it's like we
already had that experiment could you
describe what you mean by the rebirth of
the logos then in that context well it's
it's the it's part of it is taking
taking voluntary responsibility for the
appalling conditions of your life
essentially that you're a suffering
creature that's mortal right and that
you're the locus of evil both of those
things and that it's your response that
your life is about responsibility and
it's your responsibility to voluntarily
accept that and then to do what you can
about it even though it's in some sense
you know it's an enterprise doomed to
failure in some sense because you're
going to die and
and and the world is a carnage a place
of carnage
but that that you can accept that and if
you can't accept it then what that means
is that you're not integrated enough
because if your integrated enough then
you can accept it it's it's like the
test of the integration so your your
character isn't forged sufficiently if
you cannot tolerate that and it's not
like it's an easy thing to tolerate
often what people do is they just don't
think about it they just push it out of
their mind
and no wonder but they pay for that with
shallowness and with self contempt and
with with the inability to bear
suffering nobly let's say there's a call
to nobility in the in the idea of
imitation of the logos but it's more
than that it's a call to something of
well the hypothesis is it's a call to
something of cosmic significance and I
don't think that we have any right to
assume that that idea is wrong we don't
understand our place in the cosmos and
you know if you if you base your
analysis on size physical size well
there are bigger things than us but it's
not-- that's no that's not a reasonable
yardstick there isn't anything that's
more complex than us not not that we
know of so why not use that as an as a
marker Peterson is often characterized
as a religious conservative but the core
of his message has echoes of a radical
belief that organized Christianity has
fought against for generations often
called the Gnostic heresy the idea that
we can become like Jesus
you know the question is what happens to
the world around you as you embark as
you increasingly embody the logos and
the answer to that is we don't know we
don't know what the ultimate level of
this now the hypothesis is and it's a
hypothesis that extends to some degree
to Buddha as well the hypothesis is that
there has been one or two individuals
who managed that and that in their
management of that they transcended
death itself I don't know what happens
to a person if they bring themselves
completely into alignment I've had
intimations of what that might mean we
don't understand the world very well we
don't understand how the world could be
mastered if it was mastered completely
we don't know how an individual might be
able to manage that we don't know what
transformations that might make possible
there's a few quotes that you that I've
transcribed that from the ideology logos
and belief lecture which I remember
having a kind of hair stand up on the
back of my neck moment when I heard you
say this I don't know what happens to a
person if they bring themselves
completely into alignment I've had
intimations of what that might mean
that's that's mysticism rather than
religion is it not well I don't know if
you can you could draw a distinction
between those two things to some degree
because you could say that
in a religious system there's two
components and people are
temperamentally inclined to align with
one or the other there's a dogmatic
component so the Conservatives are more
likely to align with that and there's a
active mystical component which updates
the conservative component but also
threatens it so which is what creative
thought does in general and so I would
say that the mystical element of that is
religious but it's more on the
transformative side but you know I also
think that figures like the Buddha you
know he's an exemplar of the
possibilities of that alignment and the
exercise is the yogic exercises for
example our attempts to bring that
alignment into being you know I mean
it's very centered on the body which is
quite interesting even though it's a
spiritual tradition right
very very centered on the body and when
you say you have intimations of what
that might mean can you explain what you
mean by that well I've had experiences
where everything came together you know
and and and there are very very powerful
experiences and and they're they're also
characterized by it's like everything
turns into a musical symphony where each
part is exactly appropriate for that
moment and and I think music actually
expresses that which is partly why music
produces transcendent experiences you
know when people are dancing to
something profound and they're really
into it let's say the music and the
person are the same thing and then if if
things really get going you see this
sometimes in a rock concert or a musical
concert where everyone is in the same
place right the band kicks into high
gear and they're way out beyond where
they usually go you don't see that that
often in a concert even a great concert
but now and then you really see it and
the whole place is one thing that's just
pulsing you know and that's an amazing
experience and I think it is an
intimation of paradise it's something
like that
and you can think about that
psychologically you know because it also
makes sense psychologically that we're
at our best when we're integrated
completely and there is an effect of
that integration in principle on what we
would normally regard as external
reality because external reality can
line up with that integration as well
and so-called external reality and I
think people probably experience that
when they have peak sexual experiences
with someone you know where there's real
intimacy because they're in the same
place at the same time and everything
comes together for that moment you know
maybe literally yes yes literally right
and and and I also don't think that that
linguistic usage is chance right because
I think that's a place where that
experience is a brief intimation of of
heaven that might be
way of thinking about it so this message
of responsibility and meaning is
resonating most deeply with men every
public appearance that I've made that's
related to the sort of topics that we're
discussing is overwhelmingly men it's
like it's like eighty-five to ninety
percent and so I thought wow that's
weird like what the hell's going on here
exactly and then the other thing I've
noticed is that I've been talking a lot
to the crowds that I've been talking to
not about rights but about
responsibility right because he can't
have the bloody converse what are you
doing you can't have the conversation
about rights without the conversation
about responsibility because your rights
are my responsibility that's what they
are technically so you just can't have
only half of that discussion and we're
only having half that discussion and the
question is well what the hell are you
leaving out if you only have that half
of the discussion and the answer is well
you're leaving out responsibility and
then the question is well what are you
leaving out if you're leaving out
responsibility and the answer might be
well maybe you're leaving out the
meaning of life that's what it looks
like to me it's like here you are
suffering away what makes it worthwhile
right you know you're completely oh
you're completely you have no idea what
you're you it's almost impossible to
describe how bad an idea that is
responsibility that's what gives life
meaning
it's like lift a load then you can
tolerate yourself right because look at
your useless easily hurt easily killed
why should you have any self-respect
that's the story of the fall pick
something up and carry it pick make it
heavy enough so that you can think yeah
well
useless as I am at least I could move
that from there to there well what's
really cool about that is that when I
talk to these crowds about this the
man's eyes light up and that's very like
I've seen that phenomena because I've
been talking about this mythological
material for a long time and I can see
when I'm watching crowds people you know
their eyebrows lift their eyes let light
out because I put something together for
them that's what mythological stories do
so I'm not taking responsibility for
that that's what the stories do
so I save the story people go click
click click you know in their eyes light
up
but this responsibility thing that's a
whole new order of this is that young
men are so hungry for that it is
unbelievable it just blows me away it's
like really that's what's that's the
counterculture grow the hell up and do
something useful really I could do that
oh I'm so excited by that idea no one
ever mentioned that before
it's like rights rights rights rights
Jesus it's it's it's appalling it's a
it's and and I feel that that's deeply
felt by the people who are who are
coming out to to listen to these sorts
of things to there they've had enough of
that so and they better have because
it's it's a non-productive mode of being
responsibility man I think it's because
in a deep level the West has lost faith
in the idea of masculinity now that's no
different than the death of God it's the
same thing and so a Nietzsche knew what
the consequence of that would be I mean
that's most of what he wrote about you
know and so you'd say well the divine
symbol of masculinity has been
obliterated well so then what do you
expect what it what's gonna happen it's
gonna that means masculinity is going to
become weak and especially if the symbol
is also denigrated right which it
definitely is so what that means is that
the ideal that man could aspire to is
denigrated and well then with your ideal
in tatters
you're weak that's that's definitional
so I think the reason that men have been
responding positively to my my thinking
let's say is that I don't buy any of
that I like the masculine spirit it's
necessary and it's not fundamentally
carnage and pillaging it's not
fundamentally rape culture you know it's
not fundamentally world destroying and
all of those things have been all of
those aspersions have been cast upon
that's partly the guilt of Western
society for technological progress even
and those are reasonable challenges to
be set before men but they're not
reasonable accusations to swallow
without criticism and and it's not that
what is it what what is the masculinity
we can aspire to well it's a
responsibility fundamentally and it's
it's it's to put it symbolically is that
your your responsibility is to incarnate
the Spirit of the logos that's your
responsibility that's your role in life
and that is independent to some degree
in whether or not you accept the idea of
a transcendent and eternal reality now
I'm not making a case for that or
against that I those things are beyond
human understanding but we know what
happens if people act poorly if men act
badly we know what happens we know that
the world turns into something that's so
close to held that the difference is
trivial we know that that's the story of
the 20th century so we should learn that
lesson and what that lesson is is pick
up the world on your shoulders and walk
forward pick up the world with all of
its trouble with all of its suffering
with all of its evil and move forward
with it and in bearing that burden learn
that you're the sort of creature that
can bear that burden and therefore
deserving of respect that's that's the
that's identification with the logos and
that's I don't I've never encountered an
idea that's better than that because
it's not it's so not naive it's the
opposite of naive it's like there's
terrible evil and there's terrible
suffering it's bottomless
but the human spirit is capable of
voluntarily taking that on as a
challenge well it's worth a try
he believes this deep evolved truth is
under attack by a timeless resentment
relativism and cynicism under the modern
guise of the philosophy of
post-modernism people don't understand
that post-modernism is a complete
assault on two things one it's an
assault on the metaphysical substrate of
our culture and I would say that the
metaphysical substrate looks something
like a religious substrate so it's a
direct assault on that and the second
thing it's an assault on is everything
that's been established since the
Enlightenment rationality empiricism
science everything clarity of mind
dialogue the idea of the individual all
of that is is normally you see it's not
only that it's up for grabs that's not
the thing it's to be destroyed he
believes that post-modernism was the
hidden motivation for the pronoun war
and is an attack on the core structures
of being itself I assume that you're
skeptical of the idea of the description
of gender as a spectrum no I'm
suspicious of the motives for for
putting that idea forward and and I also
think it's it's it's an imprecise
definition it's not a spectrum because a
spectrum is equally represented at each
point in the distribution so that's
wrong and it and the it's wrong in the
way that you would expect it to be wrong
given its ideological basis now you know
there's male and female and masculine
and feminine are not exactly the same
thing and so and that's a reasonable
claim and you could also make a case
that too much masculinity without an
admixture of femininity is a form of
excess and that too much femininity
without an admixture of masculinity is
an X isn't is
excess you know or is a is a is a
failure
it's it's it's it's an extreme but the
obliteration of the distinction between
male and female or masculine and
feminine is a it's a psychological
catastrophe not least because those are
arguably the most basic cognitive axioms
they're deeper than that they're they're
axioms on which our entire cognitive
structures is predicated and yin-yang
yes exactly exactly exactly well and I
think that that's a consequence of our
biological heritage like the reality of
sex sex is very very very old it's a
fundamental issue and sex is
fundamentally about female and male and
there's no getting around that now as I
said you can distinguish masculine and
feminine from that and you can speak
about the psychological components of
sex as well as the physiological
components but the real radicals deny
the physiological components it's like
that's okay except when they force other
people to do the same kind of denial
like people are entitled to their
opinion but they're not entitled to put
it in the law and so that's why I was
opposed to not to transgender rights or
to transgender people or I mean it's
that's a sideshow in in many ways I'm
not trying to trivialize it but it's not
like a it's not the main event it's
emblematic of something else otherwise
no one would have cared and I just see
it as fundamentally oriented towards
destabilization and destruction he says
to defend ourselves against resentment
we each need to identify it in ourselves
our shadows
and that's partly why young believed
that it was necessary for people to
integrate their shadow and he said that
was a terrible thing for people to
attempt because the human shadow mmm
which is all those things about yourself
that you don't want to realize reaches
all the way to hell and what he meant by
that was it's through an analysis of
your own shadow that you can come to
understand why other people are capable
and you as well of the sorts of terrible
atrocities that characterize let's say
the 20th century and without that
understanding there's no possibility of
bringing it under control when you study
Nazi Germany for example or you study
the Soviet Union particularly under
Stalin and you're asking yourself well
what are these perpetrators like forget
about the victims let's talk about the
perpetrators the answer is they're just
like you and if you don't know that that
just means that you don't know anything
about people including yourself and then
it also means that you have to discover
why they're just like you and believe me
that's no picnic so that's enough to
traumatize people and that's partly why
they don't do it and it's also partly
why the path to enlightenment and wisdom
is seldom trod upon because if it was
all a matter of following your bliss and
doing what made you happy then everyone
in the world would be a paragon of
wisdom but it's not that at all it's the
it's a matter of facing the thing you
least want to face while through
listening to it started to make sense of
a lot of what I've been doing over the
last few years I've done quite a lot of
sort of deep transformational practices
a lot of shadow works of integrating the
shadow and actually feeling that real
sense of becoming more in alignment with
myself feeling that these different
parts of myself coming together and
feeling more embodied and more present
in the world but it was through
listening to you that I made this
connection with the logos with the idea
that this is actually a deep principle
of Western culture which gave it another
it's it's the principle of the
Incarnation right because the
Incarnation is is as at least a symbolic
representation of the idea that the
Spirit has to fully inhabit the body
right and that's also a remarkable it's
a
remarkable idea especially because the
spirit so to speak the psyche if you
want flees from the body in terror
because the body is the place of
mortality and suffering and so people
are disembodied and it's because what
one way of looking at is because they're
too afraid to become fully embodied and
it's no wonder they're afraid there's
reason to be afraid
but the question is well what would you
be like if you had the courage to be
fully embodied and that's fully
incarnate that's another way of thinking
about that and the idea that Christian
ideas that the fully incarnate human
being is the Messiah that's the idea
that's a hell of an idea you know but it
means embracing the horrors of the world
that's what it means and that's not only
the horrors of the world but the evil of
the world you know so there's this idea
that Christ absolutely well then those
are those are not different and you know
there's this idea that not only was
Christ the Incarnate spirit right so
fully descended into the body let's say
but that he also took the sins of the
world onto himself and what that means
is that psychologically speaking is that
part of spiritual development is to
recognize the satanic tendencies that
characterize you and to fully wrestle
with them and to and to integrate them
that's the thing it's it's not so much
to cast them away it's to transmute them
you know and you can see the difference
between people who've done that and
people who haven't at least to some
degree because people who haven't
integrated the shadow at all are naive
and you can tell that when you look at
them and you can tell that when you talk
to them and because they're naive
they're often resentful as well because
they get taken advantage of and someone
who's integrated that more they're
dangerous in in the martial arts sort of
way which is they're dangerous but they
don't have to be they don't have to use
it because their presence radiates
what would you say it doesn't radiate
threat exactly well certainly strength
but it's it's it's it's the potential
for havoc that's the right way of
thinking about it there's a there's an
implicit potential for havoc and that's
really necessary it's one of the things
that gives people self respect this is
an interesting thing about the
integration of the shadow because
recognizing yourself as the locus of
evil let's say actually in some sense
gives you far more respect for yourself
strangely enough because the same
respect that you might have for a wild
animal or even a monster it's like and
though so then maybe you learn to treat
yourself differently like I think this
is particularly true with regards to the
discipline of children you know if you
know that you're a monster and that that
will manifest itself in your life
consciously or unconsciously and if it's
unconsciously it's it's it's not good
then you become better at disciplining
children and the reason for that is that
you don't want to expose them to your
dark side and so if they behave and
don't provoke you which means they'll
also behave for other people then you
don't the monstrous part can stay in
abeyance and then that's great but if
you don't understand yourself as capable
of wreaking havoc and that can be the
kind of havoc that unfolds over decades
right because if you're going to abuse a
child
it's the primitive form of abuse is the
physical abuse the sophisticated form of
abuse is the continual undermining of
the child's courage across perhaps their
entire life and that there's a terribly
monstrous element to that and if you're
not respected properly by the child say
you will absolutely take revenge on them
and you know that's the holes in some
sense that's the whole Freudian
psychoanalytic story it's not all of it
but it's a huge part of it interesting
that you you say that you have to accept
the fact that you're dangerous or become
dangerous because I'd also say that if
you haven't done that kind of shadow
work if you haven't made friends with
your anger if you haven't integrated it
your
actually more dangerous yes then things
will happen that will it will come out
in a way that you don't expect right it
comes out disintegrate it so it comes
out as an autonomous spirit right under
no-one's control and that's like a burst
of rage let's say you either have that
or it has you those are the options and
you don't become safe by being castrated
right that's not the right move forward
you can actually see a change in
people's faces when that part of them is
integrated when the I would say the rage
circuit is integrated because their face
is hardened like they no longer look
like wide-eyed children that they're no
longer someone to whom things only
happen there there's someone who makes
things happen and there isn't much
difference between being dangerous and
being indomitable right there.this
they're that they're they're the same
thing looked at from two different
perspectives and so you know in my new
book I wrote a little bit about there
was an idea in the 80s that was
reasonably popular among psychologists
that the way to regulate male aggression
was to socialize little boys like little
girls and that's a very very bad idea
so because suppressing that aggressive
competitive urge which also
characterized as many women by the way
although it's more common among men it
that isn't what you do you you you
integrate it this is why I'm such a fan
of Piaget you know as opposed not as
opposed to Freud but I think Piaget is
developmental model is superior to
Freud's developmental model because for
Piaget the process of becoming civilized
is a process of continual integration
including the integration of what Freud
would consider the in you know I mean
it's not as if for I didn't know that
because he wanted people to incorporate
the it but he you know he kind of
conceptualized socialization as the
super-ego inhibiting the it'd you know
or or suppressing it
that's only that only happens when the
socialization process is bad when it's
good like if you have a competitive
child like my son was
was and is a competitive person you have
them integrate that into the ethos of
fair play and then it's it's a mark of
character strength at that point and
absolutely there's there's no doubt
about it
the Petersons the shadow work is another
process of embodying the logos in our
own lives by speaking the truth if you
listen to yourself talk you can tell
when when you're speaking properly you
will experience a feeling of integration
and strength and when you're speaking in
a deceitful or a manipulative manner
you'll feel that you're starting to come
apart at the seams
and what you need to do is practice only
saying things that make you feel
stronger the truth is something that
burns it burns off Deadwood and people
don't like having their Deadwood burnt
off often because they're like 95%
Deadwood and I'm not being don't believe
me I'm not being snide about that it's
no joke when you start to realize how
much of what you've constructed of
yourself is based on deception and lies
that is a horrifying realization and it
can easily be 95% of you get your things
you say things you act out many describe
how listening to them is a process of
integrating things they knew but didn't
know that they knew that's another
hallmark of truth is that it snaps
things together and people write to me
all the time and say that it's like it's
a it's it's as if things were coming
together in my mind it's like well
that's what archetypes do archetypes
glue things together so yes it's it's
the proper expression of unconscious
being teaches people what they already
know it's it's kind of like the Platonic
idea that all learning was remembering
it's right it's it's it you know in it
it's it's not right exactly the way that
we would think of learning and
remembering now but you you have a you
have a you have a nature and when you
feel that nature articulated it's it's
like the act of snapping the puzzle
pieces together they're right there
that's the that's the that's the the
bringing the levels of being in to sink
into sinker
that's what you feel it's like oh that's
synchronized now it's like what I think
and the way I feel have come together
and you feel that snap it's like oh
that's a simpler it's a simpler state
it's something like that it's not rife
with contradictions anymore
since he came to public attention
Peterson has been doing the seemingly
impossible convincing hardened atheists
of the value of religion he's a
scientist but not a materialist and
criticizes the likes of Richard Dawkins
Sam Harris this is why I have such
frustration say with people like Sam
Harris this sort of radical atheists
because they seem to think that once
human beings abandoned their their
grounding in the transcendent that the
the plausible way forward is with a kind
of purist rationality that automatically
attributes to other people
equivalent value it's like I just don't
understand that they believe that that's
the rational pathway what the hell is
irrational about me getting exactly what
I want from every one of you whenever I
want it at every possible second why is
that irrational and how possibly is that
more irrational than us cooperating so
we can both have a good time of it I
don't understand that I mean it's as if
the the psychopathic tendency is
irrational
there's nothing irrational about it it's
pure naked self-interest how is that
irrational I don't understand that
where where's the pathway from
rationality to to an egalitarian virtue
why the hell not every man for himself
and the devil take the hindmost it's a
perfectly coherent philosophy and it's
actually one that you can Institute in
the world with a fair bit of material
success if you want to do it so I don't
understa Dawkins and Harris I inhabit is
so intensely conditioned by mythological
presuppositions that they take for
granted the ethic that emerges out of
that as if it's just a given a rational
given and this of course precisely ditch
his observation as well
Dostoyevsky's that's Nietzsche's
observation you don't get it the ethic
that you think is normative is a
consequence of its of its root of its
nesting inside this tremendously lengthy
history much of which was expressed in
mythological formulation you wipe that
out you don't get to keep all the
presuppositions and just assume that
they're rationally axiomatic they're the
rational to make a rational argument you
have to start with an initial
proposition well the proposition that
underlies Western culture is that
there's a transcendent morality now you
could say that's a transcendent morality
and Stan she ated in the figure of God
that's fine you could even call that a
personification of the morality if you
want to if you if you don't want to move
into a metaphysical space I'm not
arguing for the existence of God I'm
arguing that the ethic that drives our
culture is predicated on the idea of God
and that you can't just take that idea
away and expect the thing to remain
intact midair without any foundational
support for Peterson wisdom emerges from
a much deeper place than the rational
intellect I don't consider myself an
intellectual precisely what yourself see
because my ideas aren't disembodied I
act them out but to be any less romantic
in some sense well I don't live in my
head exactly many of the prominent
intellectual types have become prisoners
of their own imagination you know it's
and this is partly what breeds that that
terror of intellectualism there's
there's something there's something
about it that's we don't want to get too
far away from our bodies we don't want
to get too far away from our souls
that's another way of thinking about it
and you know there there is this idea
that as I said before that the Catholics
always warned about is that the rational
mind falls in love with its own
productions or even more that it tries
to elevate its productions to the status
of God what are the prerequisites for
true knowledge and understanding because
it seems to me this intelligence is only
a small matter of seeing an
understanding property and it takes a
certain amount of moral courage
it's takes a certain amount of having
done the work of introspection having
done the work of deep introspection what
do you think the the components are for
true knowledge and understanding well I
think I think the motivation one of the
best motivations is existential terror
you know I mean I don't remember where
this is in the Old Testament but the
line is the fear of God is the beginning
of wisdom and that's definitely
psychologically true but but we could
strip it say of its transcendent
implications and say well if for me
anyways I wasn't motivated to be serious
until I knew what I was capable of in
the most negative way because you don't
take yourself seriously until you know
that you can be you are an evil monster
and you don't take that seriously until
you know what that means
and so but once you know what that means
especially if you do it if you find that
out consciously say then you're in a
position to start taking yourself
seriously enough so that you might be
willing to learn what you need to learn
to become wise you have to see yourself
as an Auschwitz camp guard and you have
to see yourself enjoying it and that
can't just be an exercise in
intellectual simulation precisely it has
to be a dramatic experience you have to
feel that in your bones and then you
have to decide and you have to give the
devil is do there's something very
attractive about predatory power and you
might even say that it's preferable to
pathetic weakness now I'm not saying
that but you could make a case that it
is because you could say that the person
who's pathetically weak would like to be
a predatory tyrant but just doesn't have
the ability and that's well that's a
Nietzsche and criticism of standard
morality I would say but then is there
something higher than predatory power
well
yes I mean part of part of Christ's
encounter was Satan in the desert is
precisely that realization because he's
offered the kingdom of the world and and
that means he's offered the option of
tyrannical power and his response to
that is there's something better and
that's wisdom there is something better
and there's no reason not to go for what
is the best what else you don't have
anything better to do than that by
definition right so why not work for the
betterment of being and abandon your
resentment and your hatred of humanity
and your self contempt and and take on
the responsibilities of the horrors and
and catastrophes of of human existence
and do what you can to well at least not
make it worse
but maybe to make it better you know you
can you know you can make it worse and
better you just don't know how much find
out it might be way more than you think
I'm sure that's the case so there isn't
any more an interesting adventure than
that you know find out how much good you
can do in the world and not in it and
not in this moralistic thou shalt not
way but in a forthright noble courageous
eyes wide open articulate embodied
manner and then God only knows where we
could get so let's see let's find out
that would be good it's certainly better
than the alternative
for the full 90 minute interview with
jordan peterson and more documentaries
and interviews about the biggest ideas
check out the rebel wisdom website we're
also running workshops for men to give a
direct experience of transformation
integration and purpose thank you for
watching
you